<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Huluks Blog</title>
		<description>Where I might post things ...</description>		
		<link>http://huluk.github.io</link>
		<atom:link href="http://huluk.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Radtour Oslo – Bergen, Tag 3</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;25. Mai 2015, Hedalen bis Gol&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ein ausgiebiges Frühstück mit Skyr, Wurst, Paprika und heißen Kartoffeln.
Das wärmt gut die Finger – und das ist auch nötig, denn die Schuhe sind
leider noch so nass wie am Vortag. &lt;img src=&quot;/images/3-socken_trocknen.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Nasse Socken
trocknen&quot; /&gt; Entsprechend schnell
machen wir uns auch an die Abfahrt. Nach einigen Minuten Fahrt kommen wir an
einen Ort mit Supermarkt. Wir halten kurz an, nach einem Bad und einer
Steckdose zu suchen. Ein Herr, der in der Gegend Kinder beim Spielen
beaufsichtigt, stellt sich als der Besitzer des Supermarktes heraus und
bietet uns an, dass wir noch etwas einkaufen können. Das nehmen wir an und
statten uns mit Tomatensoße, Bananen und Sonnencreme aus (die mitgebrachte
war schon bei Ankunft fast leer und gerade in den Bergen ist das schon nicht
schlecht, was dabei zu haben).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Der weitere Aufstieg ist sonnig, bis Mittag sind die Schuhe schon fast
trocken. Der Pass selbst ist eine Mautstraße. &lt;img src=&quot;/images/3-pass.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Anfang der Mautstraße,
Fahrräder frei&quot; /&gt; Ganz oben liegt eine schicke
Hochebene mit halb zugefrorenen Seen und erstaunlich vielen Häusern und
Menschen. Von de Häusern haben wir leider keine Fotos gemacht, aber das ist
schon ein richtiges Dorf oben. &lt;img src=&quot;/images/3-anfang_hochebene.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Janosh fährt auf die
Hochebene&quot; /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/3-see.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Florian vor einem
See auf der Hochebene&quot; /&gt; Höhe: fast 1000m.
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/3-oben.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Höchster Punkt des Passes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Die Abfahrt besteht dann aus sehr langen schnellen Abfahrten und längeren
flacheren Strecken zwischendurch. &lt;img src=&quot;/images/3-flach.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Zwischen den
Abfahrten&quot; /&gt; Nach einer kleinen Mittagspause
(zur Abwechslung mal Kartoffeln mit Zwiebeln und Tomatensoße) kommt dann die
finale Abfahrt. &lt;img src=&quot;/images/3-abfahrt.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Abfahrt&quot; /&gt; Im Tal liegt der
Ort Nesbyen, wo wir uns direkt in die Bahnstation begeben, um uns nach
Preisen für die Auffahrt zum Gletscher zu erkundigen. Die Überlegung ist
folgende: Auf über 1000m und Schnee zu zelten ist nicht so geil, und wir
schaffen es zwar, die 60-80km über den Pass zu radeln, aber die 1000m nach
oben sind eigentlich eine ganz eigene Etappe, die sich auch schlecht
unterbrechen lässt – jeder Meter, den unsere Übernachtung weiter unten
liegt, erhöht die Chance, dass wir nicht ganz über den Pass kommen und oben
Zelten müssen. Am Bahnsteig treffen wir einen netten Norweger, der uns
empfiehlt, noch einen Ort weiter nach Gol zu fahren, weil es da einen
Fahrkartenautomaten gibt. Die Bahnen seien meist voll ausgebucht und es wäre
sinnvoll, sich für morgen schon Tickets zu sichern. Außerdem nennt er uns
Plätze, wo es freies WLAN gibt (u.a. an allen Statoil-Tankstellen,
angeblich) und dass ein Weg am Rande unserer Route wegen eines Erdrutsches
gesperrt ist. Mit WLAN ausgestattet schauen wir nach Bahnpreisen. Laut
Bahn-Website kann man Fahrradtickets nur telefonisch buchen und die kosten
in der Saison und auf der Route Oslo-Bergen einen Pauschalpreis von über 20€
pro Fahrrad. Geil finden wir das nicht, aber erstmal ab nach Gol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Die Straße nach Gol ist anfangs sehr angenehm und eben und hat so ihre
Sehenswürdigkeiten. &lt;img src=&quot;/images/3-ponys.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Sehenswürdigkeiten&quot; /&gt; Später geht&amp;rsquo;s dann entlang einer viel
befahrenen Schnellstraße. Janosh fühlt sich etwas krank und vermutet, dass
er morgen nicht über den Pass fahren wollen wird. Darauf entschließen wir
uns, vorerst keine Tickets zu kaufen, um die Option offen zu halten, die
Bahn bis ganz nach Bergen zu nehmen. Für die Nacht lassen wir den
Campingplatz Gol links liegen, weil der ziemlich voll ist mit unmengen an
Wohnwagen. Stattdessen fahren wir den Hang hinauf durch den Vorort, bis wir
knapp in Hörweite eines Wasserfalls einen Platz für die Nacht finden.
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/3-wasserfall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Wasserfall&quot; /&gt;
Der ist immer noch mitten im Ort, aber von keinem der umgebenen Häuser
direkt einsehbar. Erneut zelten wir auf einem kaum noch benutzten Waldweg.
Das liegt daran, dass nicht von Menschen gemachte Flächen nicht allzuhäufig
eben sind und meist mit Heidekraut bewachsen. Ebene Grasflächen in der
freien Natur sind fast immer knöcheltief Sumpf.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zu Essen gibt es diesmal tatsächlich Abwechslung: Blumenkohl in Tomatensoße
zu Reis. Gefahrene Kilometer: Keine Ahnung, muss ich noch mal von Janosh
erfragen.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>http://huluk.github.io/tour/oslo-bergen-3.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://huluk.github.io/tour/oslo-bergen-3.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Learning Spanish 2</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;This is the second post about my project to learn Spanish. The final
presentation for my bachelor&amp;rsquo;s degree and travel preparations took more time
than anticipated, so that I didn&amp;rsquo;t get much done in the week before the
holidays (which was from May 22 to May 30 &amp;ndash; posts on that will follow). I
was happy to see that it only took a day of repetition to get the first
thousand words back into my head. In the last week I extensively used the
duolingo Spanish course. That one is really good and is very easy to get
into. I installed the duolingo app on my mother&amp;rsquo;s phone with an English
course for German speakers and she really likes the handling, too. The
courses are mostly based on translation tasks, whereas courses which only
teach in the target language are purportedly better for acchieving fluency.
Nonetheless it would be hard to find a higher quality online course, and
much more a free one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the goal was to learn the grammar and get into conversations. The
former I did, at least superficially. The latter not so much. Realistically
I will complete the duolingo course tomorrow and will have much to do in the
following days. maybe I can fit in some conversation over Skype, but
motivation will probably be low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewing the learning process, I&amp;rsquo;m surprised how easy everything is.
There are many verb tenses to learn and I find the rules for object placing
very confusing, but apart from that there haven&amp;rsquo;t been any major
difficulties. I&amp;rsquo;m still waiting for the shoe to drop when I reach to the
subjunctive forms and special kinds of sub-clauses, should such things exist
;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[I plan to update the structure and content of this post some time in the future. I&amp;rsquo;m posting the text in this state in order to increase the pressure to edit it. If there is no update notice here, I haven&amp;rsquo;t updated yet.]&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 06 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>http://huluk.github.io/general/learning-spanish-2.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://huluk.github.io/general/learning-spanish-2.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Learning Spanish 1</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Last week I decided to lean Spanish, roughly according to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.memrise.com/blog/can-you-learn-a-new-language-in-5-weeks/&quot;&gt;study plan&lt;/a&gt; of
Tommo Valkonen. First of, some history about why I want to do this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My interest in languages started when I was some time into learning
Esperanto and I found out that such endeavors – learning a language – are
not necessarily horrible. I began to play around with foreign grammar and
looked into some other constructed languages and finally Icelandic, which I
learned – and still learn – to some extend. However, I soon met the desire
to speak a more conventionally useful language and began to study Arabic in
parallel to Icelandic and a full university schedule. This was obviously not
planned through and I soon dropped it. So, what easy but useful languages
are out there? The list is quite short: Spanish, French, and Polish for
family reasons. I don&amp;rsquo;t currently want to put up with French spelling and
pronunciation, which leaves the other two. Reading the memrise blog post
mentioned above, I decided that a 6 week programme fits right into my
schedule: starting on May 8th and ending on June 25th, with a week of
interruption to go cycling in Norway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the plan, I first learn the alphabet and pronunciation of the
language (yup, took an hour or so). The next step is to learn the most
common words, so that I have a base for further learning. After that, I&amp;rsquo;ll
learn basic grammar and create some sentences. The rest of the time,
practice with real people over the internet. As an introvert, this will be
the hardest part for me, I really hope I&amp;rsquo;m going to follow through with
this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week, I used memrise to learn the 1000 most common Spanish
words. I heavily recommend memrise for vocab learning, but even for
oft-learned languages like Spanish, not all top listed courses are really
good. The number of learners is a good first indication of course quality,
but I recommend looking at the course forum to find out how the course
creator reacts to correction proposals. A good course also provides
information about the words (e.g. gender), but doesn&amp;rsquo;t force you to always
type the relevant markers and accepts alternative versions of words and
other words with the same meaning. For learning, I recommend practicing
daily (with obvious exceptions for vacations and special events). This is
independent of your time frame to learn the language. If you really don&amp;rsquo;t
find motivation to learn on a specific date, just repeat one or two words
and call it a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know when I&amp;rsquo;ll publish the next progress report, because there will
be a lot to do at the end of the next week. Final presentation for
Bachelor&amp;rsquo;s degree, preparation for holiday, and all. Expect something by
June 4th.
I published this post without corrections, because I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t publish it at
all would I force myself to make it perfect. Nonetheless, mayme you found it
interesting or even motivating to start learning a language yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>http://huluk.github.io/general/learning-spanish-1.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://huluk.github.io/general/learning-spanish-1.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Grove</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Birch grove. Two trees in front of you, one left and two more to the sides.
Behind them fields of wheat, glowing yellow and ripe into the lightly
clouded autumn skies.
The morning sun shines through the translucent leaves and lets you
experience an intense play of light and shadow between weeds and birches. To
the right a raven lets his call sound over the peaceful field.  None but you
and him are present, each ignoring the other with benevolent indifference.
An uncaringness as can only be offered to life with such different
aspirations as between man and bird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With your left foot you nearly stumble over a rectangular stone, two by four
handspans on ground and one in height. A curious hollow shape carved in the
middle, giving the impression of an ancient ritual place. A druid would
certainly know the magic of this copse, but today it simply invites the
lonely traveller to rest sometime, just a few steps away from the road
behind you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You realize that you hardly remember the aim of your travels, even the
existence of the road. You get the feeling that you have forgotten
something, and while you turn back to the road a darkness dawns on you, both
in the rising of a thought and in the corner of your eye. The road! You have
forgotten the road and now its world has forgotten you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The darkness you sense is the shadow of the forest before you, the
innumerous amount of pine trees stretching to infinity. You know there
only ever were a handful of them between you and the road, but now their
dark green needles stand mocking and merciless, amplifying your desperation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The raven cries again and blight befalls the trees. You never close your
eyes, but somehow the change in your environment escapes your perception:
Three barren pines stand before a batch of dirt. Dirt and puddles – both
quite familiar to your eye – stretching from horizon to horizon, guiding
your gaze through the golden fields of wheat. The raven blinks at you,
turns, and flies away.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://huluk.github.io/writing/grove.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://huluk.github.io/writing/grove.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Home</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Home&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You leave the cosy hut and go outside into the cold. A few steps through
thigh-high snow and darkness, then your eyes get used to the dimm moon
light and you see the mountains rising up even higher than your already
elevated position. The wind blows clouds of snow from the exposed cliffs on
the right of each mountain. It&amp;rsquo;s the same snow that gets blown on your face
and bites into your right cheek, while the left one only cools out from wind
alone. Every other blow lifts part of your coat and chills your intestines.
Your right boot has sunken in too deep a snow pile; the usual wetness in the
lower inches of your jeans now continues to your right ankle and beyond.
Your lips form a smile as your gaze sweeps over the mountaintops. Now at
last, the world around you perfectly mirrors the world within.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 21 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://huluk.github.io/writing/home.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://huluk.github.io/writing/home.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Mapfold</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Ich habe lange kein Erlang mehr geschrieben, jetzt kommt es in einer
Vorlesung dran. Als Fingerübung (und zum Testen des Code-Highlightings
hier) eine endrekursive mapfold-Implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-erlang&quot; data-lang=&quot;erlang&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;mapfold&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Func&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Accu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;List&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mapfold&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Func&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Accu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;List&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;mapfold&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Func&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Accu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;LiAccu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Head&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Tail&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;NewElem&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;NewAccu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Func&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Head&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Accu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mapfold&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Func&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;NewAccu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;NewElem&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;LiAccu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Tail&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;mapfold&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(_,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Accu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;LiAccu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[])&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;lists&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;reverse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;LiAccu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Accu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;



</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>http://huluk.github.io/programming/mapfold.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://huluk.github.io/programming/mapfold.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Startup</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Dies ist mein dritter Versuch, mal mit dem Bloggen anzufangen. Da ich
sowieso Zusammenfassungen zu den Inhalten meines Studiums schreiben möchte,
kann ich die ja gleich hier veröffentlichen. Das ist zwar nicht besonders
spannend, senkt aber auch die Schwelle für mich, hier andere Inhalte
reinzutun. In diesem Sinne, auf ein Neues!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besonderer Dank gilt &lt;a href=&quot;http://nino.github.io&quot;&gt;Nino&lt;/a&gt;, der mir Tipps zum Bauen
dieser Seite gegeben hat und dessen Design ich fürs Erste übernommen habe.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://huluk.github.io/general/startup.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://huluk.github.io/general/startup.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
