<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title>Huluks Blog</title>
		<description>Where I might post things ...</description>		
		<link>http://huluk.github.io</link>
		<atom:link href="http://huluk.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Learning Spanish 1</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Last week I decided to lean Spanish, roughly according to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.memrise.com/blog/can-you-learn-a-new-language-in-5-weeks/&quot;&gt;study plan&lt;/a&gt; of
Tommo Valkonen. First of, some history about why I want to do this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My interest in languages started when I was some time into learning
Esperanto and I found out that such endeavors – learning a language – are
not necessarily horrible. I began to play around with foreign grammar and
looked into some other constructed languages and finally Icelandic, which I
learned – and still learn – to some extend. However, I soon met the desire
to speak a more conventionally useful language and began to study Arabic in
parallel to Icelandic and a full university schedule. This was obviously not
planned through and I soon dropped it. So, what easy but useful languages
are out there? The list is quite short: Spanish, French, and Polish for
family reasons. I don&amp;rsquo;t currently want to put up with French spelling and
pronunciation, which leaves the other two. Reading the memrise blog post
mentioned above, I decided that a 6 week programme fits right into my
schedule: starting on May 8th and ending on June 25th, with a week of
interruption to go cycling in Norway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the plan, I first learn the alphabet and pronunciation of the
language (yup, took an hour or so). The next step is to learn the most
common words, so that I have a base for further learning. After that, I&amp;rsquo;ll
learn basic grammar and create some sentences. The rest of the time,
practice with real people over the internet. As an introvert, this will be
the hardest part for me, I really hope I&amp;rsquo;m going to follow through with
this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week, I used memrise to learn the 1000 most common Spanish
words. I heavily recommend memrise for vocab learning, but even for
oft-learned languages like Spanish, not all top listed courses are really
good. The number of learners is a good first indication of course quality,
but I recommend looking at the course forum to find out how the course
creator reacts to correction proposals. A good course also provides
information about the words (e.g. gender), but doesn&amp;rsquo;t force you to always
type the relevant markers and accepts alternative versions of words and
other words with the same meaning. For learning, I recommend practicing
daily (with obvious exceptions for vacations and special events). This is
independent of your time frame to learn the language. If you really don&amp;rsquo;t
find motivation to learn on a specific date, just repeat one or two words
and call it a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know when I&amp;rsquo;ll publish the next progress report, because there will
be a lot to do at the end of the next week. Final presentation for
Bachelor&amp;rsquo;s degree, preparation for holiday, and all. Expect something by
June 4th.
I published this post without corrections, because I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t publish it at
all would I force myself to make it perfect. Nonetheless, mayme you found it
interesting or even motivating to start learning a language yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 16 May 2015 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>http://huluk.github.io/general/learning-spanish-1.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://huluk.github.io/general/learning-spanish-1.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>The Grove</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Birch grove. Two trees in front of you, one left and two more to the sides.
Behind them fields of wheat, glowing yellow and ripe into the lightly
clouded autumn skies.
The morning sun shines through the translucent leaves and lets you
experience an intense play of light and shadow between weeds and birches. To
the right a raven lets his call sound over the peaceful field.  None but you
and him are present, each ignoring the other with benevolent indifference.
An uncaringness as can only be offered to life with such different
aspirations as between man and bird.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With your left foot you nearly stumble over a rectangular stone, two by four
handspans on ground and one in height. A curious hollow shape carved in the
middle, giving the impression of an ancient ritual place. A druid would
certainly know the magic of this copse, but today it simply invites the
lonely traveller to rest sometime, just a few steps away from the road
behind you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You realize that you hardly remember the aim of your travels, even the
existence of the road. You get the feeling that you have forgotten
something, and while you turn back to the road a darkness dawns on you, both
in the rising of a thought and in the corner of your eye. The road! You have
forgotten the road and now its world has forgotten you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The darkness you sense is the shadow of the forest before you, the
innumerous amount of pine trees stretching to infinity. You know there
only ever were a handful of them between you and the road, but now their
dark green needles stand mocking and merciless, amplifying your desperation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The raven cries again and blight befalls the trees. You never close your
eyes, but somehow the change in your environment escapes your perception:
Three barren pines stand before a batch of dirt. Dirt and puddles – both
quite familiar to your eye – stretching from horizon to horizon, guiding
your gaze through the golden fields of wheat. The raven blinks at you,
turns, and flies away.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 04 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://huluk.github.io/writing/grove.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://huluk.github.io/writing/grove.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Home</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Home&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You leave the cosy hut and go outside into the cold. A few steps through
thigh-high snow and darkness, then your eyes get used to the dimm moon
light and you see the mountains rising up even higher than your already
elevated position. The wind blows clouds of snow from the exposed cliffs on
the right of each mountain. It&amp;rsquo;s the same snow that gets blown on your face
and bites into your right cheek, while the left one only cools out from wind
alone. Every other blow lifts part of your coat and chills your intestines.
Your right boot has sunken in too deep a snow pile; the usual wetness in the
lower inches of your jeans now continues to your right ankle and beyond.
Your lips form a smile as your gaze sweeps over the mountaintops. Now at
last, the world around you perfectly mirrors the world within.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 21 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://huluk.github.io/writing/home.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://huluk.github.io/writing/home.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Mapfold</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Ich habe lange kein Erlang mehr geschrieben, jetzt kommt es in einer
Vorlesung dran. Als Fingerübung (und zum Testen des Code-Highlightings
hier) eine endrekursive mapfold-Implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-erlang&quot; data-lang=&quot;erlang&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;mapfold&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Func&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Accu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;List&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mapfold&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Func&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Accu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;List&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;mapfold&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Func&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Accu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;LiAccu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Head&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Tail&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;])&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;NewElem&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;NewAccu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Func&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Head&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Accu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;mapfold&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Func&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;NewAccu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;NewElem&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;LiAccu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Tail&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;mapfold&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(_,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Accu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;LiAccu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[])&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;lists&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;reverse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;LiAccu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;Accu&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;



</description>
				<pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
				<link>http://huluk.github.io/programming/mapfold.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://huluk.github.io/programming/mapfold.html</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Startup</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Dies ist mein dritter Versuch, mal mit dem Bloggen anzufangen. Da ich
sowieso Zusammenfassungen zu den Inhalten meines Studiums schreiben möchte,
kann ich die ja gleich hier veröffentlichen. Das ist zwar nicht besonders
spannend, senkt aber auch die Schwelle für mich, hier andere Inhalte
reinzutun. In diesem Sinne, auf ein Neues!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besonderer Dank gilt &lt;a href=&quot;http://nino.github.io&quot;&gt;Nino&lt;/a&gt;, der mir Tipps zum Bauen
dieser Seite gegeben hat und dessen Design ich fürs Erste übernommen habe.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 09 Mar 2014 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>http://huluk.github.io/general/startup.html</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://huluk.github.io/general/startup.html</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
